[SPEAKER_01]: Hello, everyone, and welcome to Method Happenings, a show for and about the city of Medford, and I am John Petrella.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the purpose of your program is to give Method citizens facts and information to help you make informed choices and also to discover city services or businesses you may not have been aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we have a special guest today
[SPEAKER_01]: And his name is Will Mubar.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is a candidate for state representative in the 34th Middlesex District.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big hello and a big welcome to you, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: We really appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We know how busy you are, your campaign, but thank you for coming on the show.
[SPEAKER_01]: We appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, John, for having me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And thank you for the opportunity.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to get right into it, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, we start our shows the same way with everyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So basically, can you tell us, you know, a little bit about yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who's Will Mubar?
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can go, like, for an entire day to talk about who I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, since this is only 40 minutes, I just want to say I'm an immigrant.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm a husband, I'm a father, I'm a public school parent, and someone who believes deeply, you know, in the promise of government, when government works for everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I came to this country from Cameroon after winning the lottery.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a green card lottery, John, and sometimes when people hear that the thing has scratched a ticket, it's just like the diversity visa lottery, and it's one in a hundred thousand people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I came to this country in 2010, never did I imagine that someday I would be entrusted with the responsibility of representing my community in elected office.
[SPEAKER_00]: I built a life here, eventually had the privilege of serving
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, the city of Somerville as a city councilor.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is my fourth term on the city council.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for more than a decade, I've worked on housing, transportation, climate, workers' rights, public safety, municipal budgets.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I'm running for state representative because the challenges we are dealing with in Somerville and Medford, like housing costs, affordability, transportation, and the rising cost of living, don't just stop at the city line.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at the high level, that is, you know, like where I am, I grew up as an orphan.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for those who don't know Cameroon, it's geographically, it's in the West of Africa, but politically it's in the center.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I know sometimes, you know, I used to just assume that people know where Cameroon is, but I've heard somebody ask me if it was in the Pacific or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I just want to put a context there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just for the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, so.
[SPEAKER_01]: It sounds like you got a lot of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, what is it about your experience, you think, that's prepared you to be an effective state representative?
[SPEAKER_01]: And I like the fact that one of the first things you said was you represent all the people.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't hear that often enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So why don't you just answer?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, what do you think?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it that's made you prepare?
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I always said that my biggest advantage is that, you know, I bring, you know, experience in city government.
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, and also my lived experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So there's all these different components.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have already near, you know, almost a decade of governing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody who has actually translated ideas into policies and actually governed on those policies.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, so when you talk about City Council, we, you know, like we have decided on how our city can spend $380 million budget.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you balance competing priorities.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how do you do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You listen to residents, negotiate with your colleagues.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then I'd be accountable for the results as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So let's say example of legislation and policies that I actually personally work on.
[SPEAKER_00]: I help create the Office of Housing Stability, help create the Somerville Community Land Trust, and also start on the Affordable Housing Trust, which appropriates
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, funds to this, you know, entity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Work on wage theft ordinance, tree protection, safe street, bicycle infrastructure, climate and environmental policies, senior issues, sanctuary, cities, welcoming policies.
[SPEAKER_00]: So these are like affordable housing and zoning reforms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the state representative's job is different, John, but the fundamental skills are the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you have to listen to people, you have to build coalition, and you have to understand the details, negotiate, and then deliver.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it sounds like you got an extreme experience working in Somerville.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, so that's been established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, you're a great candidate for the job.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you feel the state legislature operates overall?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you see a need to reform or have reform at the legislature to be more open, transparent, and accountable to the people they represent?
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I believe that people deserve to understand how decisions are made in their name.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that is fundamentally, and I also want to be very clear, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: Transparency isn't an attack on government.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is how we build trust in government.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I support more meaningful opportunities for legislators to debate legislation, you know, greater transparency around committee votes.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what we do on the city council.
[SPEAKER_00]: So in the state, it's even much more complex.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is where, you know, public access to amendments and legislative negotiations, like you have to better,
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, disclose of lobbying and procurement influence, because that alone builds stronger accountability with your constituents.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And on the city council, John, you know, residents can come to public hearing, they can testify, they can watch the debate, they can see how the elected officials vote.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I believe we should bring more of that culture of transparency to Beacon Hill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's just, this is how government should work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, and I agree with you 100%.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as we know, it doesn't seem to happen that much at the statehouse.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a great answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So following up on that now, do you support open floor votes on legislation?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I mean, let's be honest, the way things are now, some of the outcomes, you know, are a little bit predetermined by leadership before they even do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, how do you feel about that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, open floor votes and
[SPEAKER_00]: know, I think, you know, open floor vote should be, you know, a no brainer, because I believe legislators should have the ability to debate legislation and vote according to the interests of their constituents.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, that is why John, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, it's like the only thing I have, I just swept the entire city council election last fall.
[SPEAKER_00]: Top, you know, top vote getter in the city in almost every ward and every prison.
[SPEAKER_00]: So because of that integrity based leadership that I have, you know, like governed with for nearly a decade.
[SPEAKER_00]: So leadership has, you know, an important role in organizing the legislature and also building consensus.
[SPEAKER_00]: But leadership should not become a substitute for deliberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when we talk about consensus, you know, it should be built through persuasion, not simply assumed through the leadership structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: I understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and the way I see it, it's like, so if, you know, I'm elected, my constituents should know where I stand and why I voted the way I did.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, that's the way it should be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unfortunately, at the state house right now,
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't have that, but it's the way it should be.
[SPEAKER_01]: I couldn't agree with you more as far as that goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm going to just go back to one thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You did top the ticket in Somerville, correct?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I've got to ask you, I mean, topping the ticket's a great thing, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's something to be proud.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I mean, how did you manage to do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's great.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, John, I will say it is a trust, you know, in the community.
[SPEAKER_00]: I build that trust.
[SPEAKER_00]: It did not come, you know, like people got to know you, you know, you got to really show that you do care because you cannot make this thing up.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you have to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to represent the people.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so every day I go to bed, I try, you know, like to think about like, when I'm sitting in a house show, whatever decision I make, how I'm processing, you know, my thinking is that this decision, this vote I'm taking, how will it affect the least person that has no clue where City Hall is, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is the role of government.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you're always there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so people have seen that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even when I top the ticket, I always say,
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, that victory doesn't belong to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It belongs back to the people who have entrusted me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love that.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, and that's the truth.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's, you know, not many, you know, I don't want to use the term politicians too much, but not many of them think the way you think.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, that really separates you from a lot of what's going on today.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think that's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think that's, you know, a great thing for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, and it's coming from your heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: People are going to see that, and they're going to know it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you don't just talk.
[SPEAKER_01]: You walk the walk, and I think that's great, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you look at even my endorsement, it's like, you can see that there's all like, you know, there's everybody, you know, like I will engage with you because you matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as you live in the city, you pay tax, you matter to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you, you know, it doesn't, this is, that's my philosophy.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, if you live in space and there's a whole nother problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: get on, you know, like some flight to come in, you know, talk about issues that are happening in the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I love that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we got to get back to the questions now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, do you support requiring, I mean, there's a lot of lobbying activities that go on at the Statehouse.
[SPEAKER_01]: you know, procurement-based activities.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, should everything be reported and available to the public?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't seem like it is right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, how do you feel about that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, John, most of the questions you're asking, it's like so fundamental, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I think lobbying activities, including procurement related activities, should be publicly reported.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if someone is trying to influence a government decision, John, the public should be able to know who is influencing, what they are advocating for, and who is ultimately benefiting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and I've been on the other side of those conversation as a municipal official.
[SPEAKER_00]: So transparency protects both the public and the elected officials.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it makes it easier to distinguish legitimate advocacy from influence that happened behind closed doors.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I'd say 100%.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, no, it makes perfect sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know?
[SPEAKER_00]: And so for me, John, for me, lobbying is a legitimate part of our democratic process.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is when the public can see the full picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not getting the whole picture as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a big issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Big issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I know you'll do something about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: At least you'll put the effort in.
[SPEAKER_01]: All right, so something that's really affecting everyone, and it's a tough subject, and there's a lot going on with it, and you hear about it constantly, and it seems like everyone has their own way of doing this, whatever, but what's your opinion?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, affordable housing, it's tough.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's a tough thing to solve.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very important, but how do you feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, what do you do about affordable housing?
[SPEAKER_00]: I would say, affordable housing is not an abstract issue for me because I have experienced housing instability, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: I moved five times in six years.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I understand what it means for housing costs to determine what your family can and cannot afford.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, so this is an issue that is near and dear to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I have to say, I was part of the wave, you know, like Bernie Sanders actually came to some of it, believe it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I came to the city council, you know, like I was one of five city councilors.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and yes,
[SPEAKER_00]: we ran on affordability because development was also really rampant in the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I actually told myself that when I moved out of the city, which I was actually displaced, I moved to Hyde Park and then came back.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I said, if I really move permanently, I'm one less thing for those in government to worry about me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I made a conscious decision to come back.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, two years after I became a U.S.
[SPEAKER_00]: citizen, because I became a U.S.
[SPEAKER_00]: citizen in 2015, 2017, you know, and then I ran for city council and won that seat.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and on the council, I helped create the Office of Housing Stability.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, and which I mentioned in the beginning, in this office, its primary role is to help, you know, like tenants, you know, against eviction in this place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then also help, also create the, some of the community land trusts, also which, you know, you take properties and de-restrict it and build affordable housing in perpetuity.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is like, and then I've also helped increase, so that way you, we are supporting, you know, increasing housing production while also protecting tenants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not to mention that development actually creates homes that working people can afford.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my priorities have always been
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, very clear, you know, that we need to build more housing, we need to build affordable housing, we need to preserve existing affordable housing, strengthen tenant protection, because we cannot mix the two, like, oh no, we cannot separate both.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then we need to build housing near transit as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we need to support any municipality willing to increase housing production.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, of course, one of the places for building wealth is that we need to make home ownership attainable for working families.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, so we cannot solve affordability crisis by building luxury apartment, but we can, you know, we also cannot solve it by refusing to build.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see what I mean, Joe?
[SPEAKER_00]: So we need a comprehensive strategy that increases supply, protects tenants, and dramatically expands permanently affordable housing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's going to be the key, I think, is getting people to come in
[SPEAKER_01]: and build the affordable housing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just seems like there's so much red tape and everything else around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see a lot of these luxury buildings go up all over the place.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not going to give you my opinion on anything, but it just seems like
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything that's going on, I mean a lot of the things, I think the key is the affordable, building affordable houses that people can actually afford.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I always
[SPEAKER_01]: My mind always says it can't be done, and I don't know why we can't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's the political will to, you know, because a lot of time, John, people say that they want something, and then when it now comes, I don't know, it's like really interesting.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an interesting dynamic to say, oh, I want this, I want that, you know, and yet, but it should go somewhere else, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, no, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, Will, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, everyone, a lot of people now, another thing that keeps coming up is term limits.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, when I say, when I use the term, when we say term limits, most people are talking about for the speaker, the majority leader, and, you know, all these, the Senate committee chairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just seems like
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same over and over and over and over and over.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what do you feel about, you know, term limits for the Speaker, Majority Leader, committee chairs?
[SPEAKER_01]: It just seems like the same people are there constantly, and they just, here's what we're doing, and that's the way it's going to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Correct me if I'm wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're spot on, you're spot on, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I also, I don't believe in just, you know, having like some, I'm not like someone who just, again, I want, I'm open to conversation.
[SPEAKER_00]: These are all healthy conversation that should be had, you know, open to term limits for legislative leadership position, because you and I know, John,
[SPEAKER_00]: Concentrated power can become unhealthy for any institution.
[SPEAKER_00]: So at the same time, I also want to make sure that reforms actually improve the institution, rather than simply changing who holds a particular title.
[SPEAKER_00]: So for me, the fundamental question is whether ranking five legislators have a meaningful voice
[SPEAKER_00]: and whether constituents have a transparent view of the process.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I see, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so all is just to say I will support reasonable limits on leadership, tenure, and reforms that distribute power more broadly, particularly around committee assignments, hearings, amendments, and floor votes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all, that's good to hear because, you know, it just seems like, and I think one of the, you know, the things most people talk about, you know, up at the, you know, the Statehouse and Beacon, whatever, you know, Beacon Hill, whatever terms we use, it just seems like, and I, we need change up there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my opinion.
[SPEAKER_01]: I usually don't give my opinion, but it's like we need,
[SPEAKER_01]: change.
[SPEAKER_01]: We need people to get in there and actually make these changes or are willing to make these changes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think you're the kind of guy, in my opinion, again, that's going to do this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean,
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm going to make every effort to make a difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to see progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to be the kind of person that just... For me, it's about making progress and then be accountable back to your district.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fundamental so that people see.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is why everybody... The people who have been with me, who have been supporting me for nearly a decade, they don't need to figure me out.
[SPEAKER_00]: The people who don't know me can get up some day and say, oh, well, Will seems like a nice guy.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does he stand for?
[SPEAKER_00]: I stand for community, because I came from the community.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know where you came from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you care about where you came from, and you're not going to forget where you came from.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: It really is, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you come across.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a compliment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's a big compliment, because that is how you come across, like you really do care.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes a lot of work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing happens overnight, but you've got to sort of persevere, I guess.
[SPEAKER_01]: So here's another question, and I hate to say it, Will, but this is sort of like affects me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I never admit this, but I'm a senior citizen now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I see a lot going around, a lot of things going on, Medford, Somerville, everywhere with senior citizens.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, my parents, their generation in this state, cities, whatever, there was stability there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they always had stability.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just seems like it's not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a lot of seniors, you know, they all worked hard.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they did what they had to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: but it's expensive to live right now for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it just seems like we're not, in my opinion, we're not getting enough done for seniors.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems like a lot more of them are struggling to get by.
[SPEAKER_01]: They've been in the same house, you know, for 40 years, you know, the taxes go, everything keeps going up.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only thing that doesn't go up
[SPEAKER_01]: is the pay.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're on the social security, their pension.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't get increases anymore is what I'm trying to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you're retired, you work very hard, and I know a lot of them went back to work part-time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So I mean, this is a tough one, but is there anything that can be done to maybe bring some stability to the older folks?
[SPEAKER_00]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_00]: John, no, this is really something also that I, you know, it's a very important question when you even mentioned that you're a senior, like you look like 25.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm like, is he trying to get a senior discount or something?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, John, I have to say, you know, when seniors tell,
[SPEAKER_00]: us that they are worried about whether they can afford to stay in the community where they raise their families.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a failure we need to address.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is point blank.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not subject for debate.
[SPEAKER_00]: various ways that we, you know, we need to look at how the seniors, you know, need, you know, support.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, we've done, you know, some work in the city, but I would just scale, you know, up the conversation because you really asked about like how
[SPEAKER_00]: we can actually, you know, help seniors.
[SPEAKER_00]: We can help them, you know, through housing, utilities, you know, healthcare and transportation.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is, I think this is how we've really attacked these issues, you know, in the city.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is at a state level is going to be really big because for housing,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, senior affordable housing is something that we got to focus on property tax relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is something that, you know, we need to like, you know, look into programs that allow seniors to age in place, you know, and protect them from displacement.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the housing piece.
[SPEAKER_00]: that we need to, because sometimes it's very easy to mix all these things together.
[SPEAKER_00]: For utilities, we make sure that how do we support seniors, lower their energy costs, you know, like kind of like change their housing like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: weatherization, like kind of like create this energy efficient building so that, because most of the buildings are old, you know, and efficient, you know, and that way, you know, once you're assisting the utility bills, it's pretty clear that you've done the things that you needed to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then again, protect access to healthcare and prescription drugs.
[SPEAKER_00]: We hear that all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's and then some seniors also like the home based care.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is something that they need support with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So this is something that we cannot ignore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then when you talk about transportation, reliable and accessible public transportation, we actually did that in some of the senior friendly street and sidewalk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Believe it or not, John, one of the things that is so sad that I've seen in the US, you know, I mean,
[SPEAKER_00]: I can talk about some of it, but it's just everywhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're a senior and you're a person with disability, you're almost invisible, which is sad.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's really sad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So our seniors, you know, shouldn't have to choose between paying their property taxes, paying their heating bill and buying their medication.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a lot.
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, for us, you know, to be able to ask them to process that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we need policies that allow people who have contributed to our communities for decades to remain part of those communities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I know sometimes people, you know, some people, oh, well, if you can't, maybe you should go live somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's easy to say that we're all going to get old, we're all going to be disabled, and we're not...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the golden rule, like, you know, treat other people the way you want to be treated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, no, I love that, the golden rule, that's right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you know, I just, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: I just think that a lot of seniors and, you know, and I understand, you know, things go up, taxes go up, everything else, but I think it's very important for these, you know, for seniors to stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, they own a two-family house, a single-family house, whatever it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, there's a lot of them, you know, living at senior centers and a lot of people
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, they do a great job, I mean, helping seniors.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are some programs out there, but, you know, it's tough.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I think, I mean, you answered it well, but I just think that's, I don't think it gets looked at enough, that's all, you know, one of those things, you know, so.
[SPEAKER_00]: We got to do more for our seniors, for sure, because this is like the time where we all
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, have to come together and think about like the implication of most of the policies that we are doing, especially now at the state level, you know, people will be depending on us.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like so many programs, you know, that are going to be facing away.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do we kind of like make sure that there's funding for, you know, like the meals, they don't, you know, their housing situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is like, it's like really like fundamental stuff that will help really build trust
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, and the seniors can believe back in, you know, their own government, that government is there to help them, you know, support.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also like in the city, I was advocating for senior liaison position in the mayor's office, because there's like this Council on Aging, this is how we use that office to help seniors.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then we also work through Mass Senior Action Council.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then some of them had told me, well, we need a senior liaison person.
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, that can really just help us with our tech support, coach, volunteer program, you know, assist with our computer issues.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that is something that, you know, we need to do, because if they're asking for something like that, it means that they need help for particular issues, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but we've really helped with the discount for transit fare for low income.
[SPEAKER_00]: So we've done that in some of the buses, and then we've piloted, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: you know, even a free bus passes for seniors, just to ensure that they can also take their taxi to their, you know, for, for their medication to, they can take, like, we're helping them.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was a grant that we use.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To provide transportation, you know, for senior.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then we kind of like,
[SPEAKER_00]: remove that grant from ARPA and then put that in the general budget, just so that we can continue to serve our seniors.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's a great idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, every little bit helps, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a good program.
[SPEAKER_01]: I heard of that program, by the way, so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gotcha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hey, you know, Will, I could probably go on for another hour and talk to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But unfortunately, you know, we have a 35, 40-minute show.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I can't thank you enough for coming on the show today.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's been a pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I wish you, and I know you're out there campaigning because a lot of my friends have seen you talk about you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, you know, hopefully this program, people will get to know you better.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think my
[SPEAKER_01]: personal opinion, you're going to make a great state rep.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wish you continued success.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've been a great Councilor, and I think you're going to be a great state rep.
[SPEAKER_01]: So thank you so much for joining us.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we really appreciate you coming on the show.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you for taking the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any time, John.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know I'm doing the work because again, I'm the guy from Cameroon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing was handed to me and I don't take anything for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know you don't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was great.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was great to have you on.
[SPEAKER_01]: a nice job explaining who you are, what you believe in, and that's a great thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So once again, thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll be talking to you soon.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure I'll see you around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anytime.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hopefully, I'll be honored to have the opportunity to represent Medford and Somerville as their next day representative.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I just hope that they will consider to give me their vote on September 1st and visit my website for details and seeing my track record and also consider supporting my campaign.
[SPEAKER_01]: The last thing I want to hear from you right now is, what is your website?
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's get it out there so people can go check it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So my website is Will, W-I-L-L, and then my last name, M-B-A-H, M as in man, B as in boy, A as in apple, H as in house, willmbar.com.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say it one more time, and then we're going to end it.
[SPEAKER_01]: One more time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will, W-I-L-L, and then M-B-A-H, so willmba.com.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everyone's got to check it out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once again, thanks, Will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'll see you around the campaign trail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_00]: God bless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Best wishes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thank you, Joe.
[SPEAKER_01]: OK, it's that time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to take a minute to thank everyone who has been watching the show and thank you for your feedback.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you would like to appear on the show, you can contact us at methodhappenings02155 at gmail.com and you will be able to watch replays of this program
[SPEAKER_01]: on Method Community Media Access Channel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can also check out our website, MethodHappenings.com, where you can now either view or listen to the podcast of this program.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can find all of our shows, as usual, on YouTube.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just go to YouTube.com, search for Method Happenings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Please like and subscribe to our channel and our videos.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can also find us on Facebook at MedFedHappenings.
[SPEAKER_01]: We also have our own subreddit, which you can find us at reddit.com slash MedFedHappenings.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's reddit.com slash MedFedHappenings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you all for watching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for the Method Happenings team, Paul, Marco, Bruce, James, Joseph, and me, I'm John Petrolla.
[SPEAKER_01]: And remember Method, stay informed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you.